｢there was a hungry crow｣
｢who wanted to get some feed｣
｢if only this beak were longer｣
that feed would be a bit closer
｢a crow can think｣
｢can think... can think｣
Observe, propose a hypothesis, experiment, and then reflect.
Learn the way of scientific thought.
We begin with a ｢Thinking Observation｣
Today we observe the sounds a train makes.
This 'click-clack' noise. What's making it?
We observe from outside the train.
The 'click-clack' noise doesn't come from here.
Let's try moving.
The 'click-clack' noise comes from here.
How is this place different from the last?
Let's try comparing the two places.
If we pay close attention to the rails...
Here, there's something attached to the rails.
Let's observe the noise while watching this place closely
Each time the train wheels pass here...
We hear the noise.
What on earth is this?
If we look very carefully...
there's a gap in the rails.
If we look from the side...
The crack widens.
Does the sound arise when the train wheels pass over this gap?
By shifting a desk, we tried to make such a gap at home.
It certainly does make a sound.
♪
～
Well then, today our problem deals with a pipe and some balloons.
A large balloon and a small one are attached on either side of the pipe.
The two balloons are of the same type.
The interior of this pipe is hollow.
But here there is a valve, which closes the pipe.
So therefore, the air in the two balloons
can't move freely between them.
When we twist here, the valve inside opens.
the air in the two balloons can then come and go freely.
Now this is the problem.
When I open this valve...
How do you think the balloons will change?
1 The large balloon will increase in size further, and the smaller balloon will shrink.
2. The large balloon will shrink and both ballons will assume the same size.
3. The balloons will remain unchanged.
We'll reveal the answer at the end of the program.
Everyone, please think about it won't you?
Observation, hypothesis, experiment, and then reflection.
Thinking scientifically...
And now the answer to our problem.
Everyone, did you think carefully?
1. The larger ballon will grow bigger and the small balloon will shrink.
2. The larger balloon will shrink and both balloons will assume the same size.
3. They will remain unchanged.
Well then, let's try it.
What will happen to the balloons?
Watch carefully, won't you?
The larger balloon became even larger
and the smaller balloon shrunk.
Let's watch that one more time.
The answer is that the larger balloon will increased further in size
and the smaller balloon shrunk.
Why do you suppose that is?
The secret is that inside each balloon there is air pressure.
Inside the larger balloon that pressure is lower...
from here on we think for ourselves.
Now everyone is a thinking crow.