♪
｢There was a hungry crow｣
｢Who wanted to get some feed｣
♪
｢If only this beak were only longer｣
｢That feed would be a bit closer｣
♪
～
｢A crow can think｣
♪
｢can think... can think｣
Observe, propose a hypothesis, experiment and consider results.
Learn the way of scientific thought.
We begin with a Thinking Observation.
Today we observe a strange pheonenon using coins.
Hold up a single one yen and two ten yen coins between your fingers.
This ten yen coin remains above.
The lower two coins drop.
The one yen coin above and the 10 yen coin below.
If we drop these two coins...
The one yen coin ends up on top.
Did they switch en route?
Let's do it once more.
Once more the one yen coin went to the bottom.
As we thought they switched positions.
Let's try a different combination.
We add another 10 yen coin underneath.
Leaving the single ten yen coin above in place, we drop the three below.
Doing so, we confirm the three coins have changed position.
Will the one yen coin end up at the bottom?
The one yen coin ended up in the middle.
Let's try once more.
It's the same.
Let's try to organize this on paper.
At the start 1 yen 10 yen became 10 yen 1 yen.
Next if we add another 10 yen coin below.
It changed this way.
We don't understand this well.
What will happen with a different arrangement.
This time we dropped the one yen coin in the middle.
And it ended up underneath.
Let's also confirm this on paper.
Looking carefully at the results..
We can see some regularity.
♪
～
Given that, what will happen with this arrangement?
Thinking Observation.
♪
～
We will reveal the answer in the next program.
Today's problem uses a pendulum.
Grabbing the ball and release it.
Look, it swings well.
This is a pendulum.
Actually, the pendulum we're using is special.
The weight at the end is a powerful magnet.
If we bring it close to a clip.
it sticks to it firmly.
♪
～
But here we have prepared an aluminum plate.
And to this
it doesn't stick at all.
Magnets don't stick to aluminum.
Now this is the problem.
The aluminum plate that this magnet will not stick to
we place it on the desk.
And we separate the magnet from it.
If we do this how will the pendulum swing?
1. It will go slower than the case with no plate.
and stop.
2. Just the opposite. It will go faster and not stop at all.
３｡
3. It will swing the same as if there were no plate.
Well then what will happen?
We'll present the anser at the end of the program.
Everyone, please think hard won't you?
♪
～
And now the answer from earlier.
Everyone did you think carefully?
Then, let's do it for real.
First we try the case without the plate beneath.
This is the normal state.
Now we try with the aluminum plate beneath.
How do you think the pendulum will swing?
Watch really closely, won't you?
It stopped right away.
Let's try once more.
The answer is 1.
It was "the pendulum will swing more slowly than the case without the plate
and stop right away."
But magnest ought not stick to aluminum.
Why should this happen?
This is connected to a propery between magnets and aluminum.
Magnets don't stick to aluminum, but it conducts electricity.
And magnets and electricity...
From here on we think for ourselves.
From here on we're all thinking crows.