｢There was a hungry crow｣
｢Who wanted to get some feed｣
｢If only this beak were a little longer｣
｢That feed would be a bit closer｣
｢A crow can think｣
｢can think... can think｣
Observe, propose a hypothesis, then experiment and consider results.
Learn the way of scientific thought.
We begin with a Thinking Observation
Look closely at the sand in this aquarium.
It's all stripey.
It's separated into three colors, like geological strata.
Why is it separated into these colors?
If we look at it the next morning...
The stripes are gone.
The sand is all a uniform color.
What's going on here?
Let's try looking at it at the original time.
If we look at it at night again we see the sand separated into 3 colors.
It only comes out at night?
As a test, let's poke the sand.
Hunh? When we move the sand...
the layers underneath move with it.
If we pile it up, the layers underneath also pile up.
Why should this be?
Let's try observing for a little while.
Ahh. We can see somethig beneath the hermit crab.
Something like a shadow.
is being cast on the lower layers.
Is this some kind of shadow?
Let's try testing with a pair of tweezers.
When we lower it into the water
as we thought, something like a shadow is cast.
This shadow like thing
might it have something to do with the light illuminating the aquarium?
Let's try turnig the light off.
The stripes disappeared.
Let's try moving the light.
The stripes moved.
As we thought, this light is the true cause of the stripes.
But as we think further it seems a bit strange.
When the light shines on these tweezers
The shadow ought only be cast onto this desk.
and yet somehow a shadow appears in the sand?
Dedenion
Hypothesis
love
Episode 3: The Mysterious Footprints
Dedenion
Animation: milligram
Today's problem deals with this triangular stand and a ball bearing.
This triangular stand is placed on a scale.
There's a rail attached to this stand.
There's a little tape attached at the top of the rail.
firmly fixing the ball in place.
When the ball is sitting there...
it's exactly 200 grams.
The weight of the ball and the stand together.
Now this is the problem.
A short time later the ball will come off the tape
it will begin rolling.
While the ball is rolling down this incline
what will happen to the displayed weight?
1. The weight will increase.
2. The weight will remain at 200 grams
3. The weight will decrease.
Well, what will happen?
We'll present the answer at the end of the program.
Everyone, please think hard about it, won't you?
Observation, hypothesis, experiment and reflection.
Thinking scientifically. Thinking Crow.
And now the answer from earlier.
Everyone, did you think about it carefully?
Q: When the Ball starts to roll what will happen to the weight on the scale?
1. The weight will increase.
2. The weight will remain at 200 grams.
3. The weight will decrease.
Then, let's try it for real.
We affix the ball to the tape and remove our hands.
We wait for the ball to come free from the tape on its own and start rolling.
Because if I touched it even a small amount
the indicated weight would easily change.
Well then, what will to the weight?
Please look closely at the weight shown on the scale, please.
Did it change?
Let's look at that one more time
Then the answer...
Why do you think this is?
When the ball is held by the tape...
The weight of the ball is entirely contributed to this stand.
But when the ball is rolling...
From here on we think for ourselves.
From here on we're all thinking crows.